<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The royal law contended for, or, Some brief grounds serving to prove that the Ten Commandments are yet in full force, and shall so remain till heaven and earth pass away. Also the seventh day Sabbath, proved from the beginning, from the law, from the prophets, from Christ, from his apostles, to be a duty yet incumbent upon saints and sinners. / By a lover of peace with truth Edward Stennet.</title>
            <author>Stennett, Edward, d. 1690?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 113 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93852</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5402B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R184622</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43078167</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43078167</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151754</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93852)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151754)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2275:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The royal law contended for, or, Some brief grounds serving to prove that the Ten Commandments are yet in full force, and shall so remain till heaven and earth pass away. Also the seventh day Sabbath, proved from the beginning, from the law, from the prophets, from Christ, from his apostles, to be a duty yet incumbent upon saints and sinners. / By a lover of peace with truth Edward Stennet.</title>
                  <author>Stennett, Edward, d. 1690?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Exeter College Library, Oxford, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ten commandments --  Biblical teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sabbath --  Biblical teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151754:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ROYAL LAW CONTENDED FOR OR, Some Brief Grounds ſerving to prove that the Ten Commandements are yet in full force, and ſhall ſo remain till Heaven and Earth paſs away.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>ALSO</hi> The Seventh Day Sabbath, proved from the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, from the Law, from the Prophets, from Chriſt, from his Apoſtles, to be a duty yet incumbent upon Saints and Sinners.</p>
            <p>By a Lover of Peace with Truth <hi>Edward Stennet.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>They that forſake the Law praiſe the wicked, but ſuch as keep the Law contend with them,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 28.4.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Let us hear the concluſion of the whole matter, Fear God and keep his Commandments, for this is the whole duty of man,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Eccleſ. 12.13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>The Sabbath was made for man, and not man for the Sabbath; therefore the Son of man is Lord even of the Sabbath,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Mark. 2.27, 28.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then ſhall I not be aſhamed when I have reſpect to all thy Commandments,</hi>
                  <bibl>Pſal. 119.6.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed in the Year 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:151754:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151754:2"/>
            <head>TO ALL That truly fear the LORD, and tremble at his Word.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was not in the leaſt my purpoſe to expoſe the enſuing diſcours to publique view, but to communicate it onely to ſome private Chriſtian friends, as a reaſon of the hope that is in me, in relation to the Law of the Lord. I being in a good meaſure, ſenſible of my own weakneſs and unfitneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for ſuch a work, but the Lord was pleaſed to bleſs theſe my weak endeavours with the ſucceſſes of conviction to ſome, and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to others of his dear ſervants, who were my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragers (after ſolemne waiting upon our Heavenly Father) unto this, which I can truly ſay, I was dead unto; although I was and am perſwaded that the gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt the truth therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, but my weakneſs in the management of it was the great obſtruction. But I am willing to preſs after a likeneſs to Jeſus Chriſt, who made himſelf of no reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:151754:3"/>and to learn of him who was meek and lowly in heart.</p>
            <p>I am not ſo conceited to preſent this Treatiſe as a thing that's rare or new, either to the Saints or World, for if they will look about them, they may ſee this truth in a better dreſs and luſtre; but it may be the tender Lambs and Sucking-Babes of Jeſus Chriſt may better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand my ſtammering tongue then thoſe that ſpeak more diſtinctly, and that's one main encouragement to me I do profeſs in the preſence of him who tryes the heart and reines; Light hath broak forth ſince I wrote theſe papers about the Law in general, and the Sabbath in particular: it being five or ſix months ſince they were written, yet notwithſtanding I am now encouraged by the Lord I truſt, and by his people, (to ſpeak this on the houſe top which was ſpoken to me in ſecret,) becauſe ſo many of the Lords people are ſo deluded that they have rejected the Law of God, and live in a weekly profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of his Holy Sabbath, thinking that Chriſt abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht the whole Law at his death, though Chriſt utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nys it, and would have none to harbour ſuch a thought, <hi>Mat. 5.17.</hi> although many of the men of this opinion may be good, yet it makes their error not one Jote the better. <hi>For this flows from their carnality and not their ſpirituality; for the carnal mind is not ſubject to the Law of God, neither indeed can be,</hi> Rom. <hi>8.7.</hi> But becauſe truth ſprings up out of the earth, and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs looks down from Heaven, and the ancient ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable inſtitution of Jehovah now begins to ſhine with ſuch clearneſs, that it cannot be razed out of the tables, and therefore all is caſt away together, which is ſuch an invention as would not have been thought on by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, I am certain, if Sabbath Light had been concealed.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151754:3"/>
            <p>The two ancient inſtitutions of the Lord in Paradiſe were Mariage and the Sabbath, both which are called and eſteemed honorable, Heb. <hi>13.4. Marriage is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable in all;</hi> and in <hi>Iſay 58.13.</hi> the Sabbath is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Holy of the Lord, honorable; and Chriſt leads us to the beginning of them both, when the queſtion was whether men might put away their wives for every fault, the anſwer is, <hi>that Moſes did but ſuffer it to be ſo, becauſe of the hardneſs of their hearts, but from the beginning it was not ſo,</hi> Mat. <hi>19.34, 35.36, 37.</hi> and when the Phariſees were ſo ignorant, that they thought works of mercy were not to be done upon the Sabbath day, Chriſt leads them to the firſt inſtitution of it, and tels them it was made for man, <hi>Mark. 2.24, 27.</hi> Both theſe inſtitutions were made for the good and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of man in his Paradiſe eſtate, which is ſufficient proofe for their duration. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>that the man was not created for the woman, but the woman for the man, 1</hi> Cor. <hi>11.9.</hi> and our bleſſed Lord of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath ſaith that the Sabbath was made for man, and not man for the Sabbath.</p>
            <p>Then Chriſtians be noble ſpirited and ſearch the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures with all readineſs of mind and with hearts lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging after truth; get as remote from earth and earthly things as you can, and into the ſecret chamber of your beloved, and when you are the moſt tranſported from earth to heaven in near and cloſe communion with him, then try and judge by his word and ſpirit, weighing Scripture with Scripture in an equal ballance, and be as cautious in taking up objections againſt this truth, as you are of being in the practiſe of it. T'is ſad to ſee, and that which wounds my ſpirit much, that perſons profeſſing godlineſs ſhould be ſo inconſiderate as to
<pb facs="tcp:151754:4"/>catch at any thing that comes next to hand, to ſtrike at that which a differing Saint affirms is truth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſidering the weight of what is offered, or whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their own objections lead them; I have ſeen more gall and wormwood at the bottom of thoſe objections that have been made againſt the Sabbath, then ever I ſaw in any objections againſt any other command, and even ſome Chriſtians are ſo weak that all paſſes for cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that flows from a man that's good, and able, but where are thoſe virgin ſpirits that are redeemed from the earth, and from among men that lay perſons, intereſts &amp; cuſtomes by, whileſt they judge between truth and error, where ever they are, they are men which will follow the Lamb, when others are left behind. They will not be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted at the ſeventh day Sabbath, becauſe nicknamed, &amp; called the Jews Sabbath no more then they are at the God of the Jews; they will not refuſe to keep the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath becauſe a man was ſtoned, any more then they will refuſe <hi>Jehovah</hi> to be their God, becauſe thoſe that worſhip ſtrange Gods were to be put to death: and if they be told they go back to the Law, they can an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>bleſſed are they that do his Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that they may have right to the Tree of Life, and may enter in through the gate into the City,</hi> when the breakers of the Law are left without. <hi>Rev. 22.14, 15.</hi> Do you therefore that fear the Lord and think upon his name, lye down at his feet and cry earneſtly for his ſpirit to lead you into all truth; that you may not kick againſt the pricks in this chaſtiſing day, wherein the Lord is teaching his people out of his Law, and fitting them for the Kingdom of glory, which is at the door. Now the Lord is diſcovering every part and piece of Babylon, that the Saints may know the
<pb facs="tcp:151754:4"/>better how to reward her; but becauſe the Saints begin to own the Lord as King and Law-giver, the Dragon is wroth, and knows that this will deſtroy his Kingdom, and ſo would endeavour to perſwade perſons that the Law of God is aboliſhed, well knowing that if he could perſwade them to abelief of this, they will ſoon ſay there is nothing to be done till Chriſt come in perſon.</p>
            <p>I would not make too large a gate to ſo ſmall a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but ſhall haſten to a concluſion with a word to the little remnant that keep the Sabbath according to the Commandement. Precious Brethren, you are under great and precious promiſes for your encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagement, though your oppoſers are great and nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous. I think often of what is ſaid of <hi>Aſher,
<note place="margin">Deut. <hi>33.24, 25.</hi>
                  </note> Let Aſher be bleſt with children, let him be acceptable to his brethren, and let him dip his foot in oyl, his ſhooes ſhall be Iron and Braſs, and as is his dayes, ſo ſhall his ſtrength be.</hi> Aſher ſeems to hold forth the remnant that the Lord will uſe in the latter dayes to tread down the wicked withal; <hi>and</hi> Aſhers <hi>bread ſhall be fat, yea he ſhall yield Royal dainties,</hi> Gen. <hi>49.20.</hi> and if you my Brethren, <hi>fulfil the Royall Law according to the Scripture, ye ſhall doe well;</hi> though your Brethren frown upon you at preſent, yet you ſhall be acceptable unto them: and what if your work be difficult, if your ſtrength be ſutable, you need not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain; you may tread upon Scorpions if your ſhooes be Iron and Braſs; your feet will be like Hinds feet if they be dipt in oyl, which will
<pb facs="tcp:151754:5"/>cauſe you to run without wearineſſe, and walk without fainting;</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>So he prayes,</hi> 
               <signed>Who is only through grace a ſervant of <hi>CHRIST,</hi> though unworthy to be ſo called, EDWARD STENNET.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151754:5"/>
            <head>Some Brief Grounds, ſerving to prove that the Ten Commandements are yet in ful force, and ſhall ſo remain till Heaven and Earth paſſe away.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, The matter of the Ten Commandements was written in the Heart of <hi>Adam</hi> before his fall, as doth appear <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.27. <hi>God created man in his own Image, in the Image of God created he him.</hi> Eccleſ. 7.29. <hi>God hath made man upright, but he ſought out many inventions.</hi> And the Apoſtle plainly aſſerts, that the Gentiles, which had not the Law, (in the letter of it) did by nature the things contained in the Law, which ſheweth the work of the Law written in their hearts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14, 15. Now if the Gentiles had the work of the Law written in their bearts, in their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſtate, doubtleſs they had it in more perfection in their ſtate of innocency, as conſidered in <hi>Adam;</hi> for the letter of the Law was added, becauſe of tranſgreſſion, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.19. Now if there were tranſgreſſion before the letter of the Law was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that implies there was a Law before; and in that the letter of the Law is ſaid to be added, it implies that the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it was in being before, but much worn out by ſin; and that is one reaſon why the Lord was pleaſed to add the letter.</p>
            <p>Let it be conſidered how it can ſtand with Scripture, or right reaſon, that Jeſus Chriſt ſhould abrogate this Law; did Chriſt blot out this Law out of the hearts of all men by his death?
<note place="margin">Rom. 2.15.</note> then all men have not the Law of Nature to guide them; for we cannot be ſo groſs as to imagine that the Law is put into their hearts upon a new account, for that were to bring all men under the new Covenant.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God ſpake all theſe Commandments unto the people, and they heard his voice, <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.22, 23, 24. with great Majeſty and Glory, and he added no more; and he wrote them upon
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:151754:6"/>two Tables of Stone, and delivered them unto <hi>Moſes;</hi> all which holds forth their perpetuity, they are ſpoken by God, they are wrote by him in Tables of Stone; ſo was never any Ceremony. <hi>Job</hi> deſires that his words were graven with a pen of Iron and Lead, in a rock of ſtone for ever, Chap. 19.24.</p>
            <p n="3">3. After the firſt tables were broke, which I ſuppoſe did ſignifie the Iſraelites breaking of the firſt Covenant; for <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> brake them upon that account,
<note place="margin">Behold the Ark as it ſtands under the mercy feat.</note> they having made a Golden Calf, and ſo had broke the Commandement: <hi>Moſes</hi> was then commanded to hew two Tables like unto the firſt, and God wrote the ſame words again upon them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.1, 2, 3, 4. and they only of all the Laws were put into the Ark; and when the Ark is ſet in its proper place between the Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bims, there is nothing in it but the two Tables, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.9. Now the Ark was a Type of Chriſt, and the putting the Law into it did ſignifie the putting of it into the heart of Chriſt, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 40.6, 7, 8. <hi>Thy Law is in my heart:</hi> and from thence they are tranſcribed into the hearts of the ſeed of Chriſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the new Covenant, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33. <hi>Where God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to put his Law in their inward parts, and write it in their hearts.</hi> Now what Law is this that muſt be put in the heart, when the Law of ſacrifice is aboliſhed? <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.6, 7, 8, 9. compared with that forementioned in the Pſalmes, that this is the Law that is here ſpoken of is manifeſt, if we conſider firſt how proper and ſuitable it is for the heart of a believer. <hi>Paul</hi> calls it <hi>the Law of his mind,</hi> Rom. 7.23. and in 22. he profeſſeth he delights in the Law of God after the inward man; and God ſaith, <hi>he will put his Law in the heart, and write it there;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.2, 3.</note> both which phraſes hold it forth to be the ſame Law that was wrote by God, and put into the Ark: mans heart is the Tables, and God himſelf is the writer, the matter written is the Law: and hear what Wiſdome ſaith to this, <hi>Prov.</hi> 7.1, 2, 3. <hi>My ſon keep my words, and lay up my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements within thee, keep my commandements and live, and my Law as the apple of thy eye, bind them upon thy fingers, write them upon the table of thine heart.</hi> Now what Laws are theſe but the Table-Laws, which were then in being, and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms ſon is to have them writ upon the fleſhly Tables of his heart.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:151754:6"/>
            <p n="4">4. When God promiſeth to exalt his firſt-born higher then the Kings of the Earth, and that his Covenant ſhould ſtand faſt with him, <hi>Pſal,</hi> 89.28, 29. <hi>and that his ſeed ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure for ever, and his Throne as the dayes of Heaven:</hi> yet he ſaith, <hi>If his Children forſake my Law, and walk not in my judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, if they break my Statutes, and keep not my Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> verſ. 30, 31. <hi>Then will I viſit their tranſgreſſion with a rod, and their iniquity with ſtripes,</hi> verſ. 32. <hi>Nevertheleſſe my loving kindneſs will I not utterly take away, nor ſuffer my faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſse to fail.</hi> Mark it, this Covenant was with Chriſt, (though with <hi>David</hi> in the Type) in the behalf of all the ſeed: and chaſtiſements muſt be the portion of the ſeed, if they break the Law of God, though his Covenant ſtand faſt: now as this Covenant reaches all the ſeed, ſo doth the Law, and the puniſhment for the breach of it; and if ſo, then what Law is it that reaches all the ſeed, if not the Law of the Ten Commandements, with thoſe Laws which are comprehended in them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Theſe Commandments are eminently diſtinguiſhed and marked out from all the Ceremonial Laws, both to ſhew their eminency and perpetuity, they are ſaid to be the work of God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.16. and the Pſalmiſt ſaith, <hi>The works of his hands are verity and judgement;</hi> and theſe works are called, <hi>all his Commandments,</hi> Pſal. 111.7. and they are Ten, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.13.<note place="margin">Exod. 34.28.</note> And therefore I conceive Wiſedoms ſon is to bind them upon his fingers, to ſhew the number of them, there being for each finger one, and that both hands might be active in them. And <hi>Zachary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> are ſaid <hi>to walk in all the Commandments and Ordinances of the Lord,</hi> Luke 1.6. They are diſtinguiſhed from the Cerimonial Ordinances, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>all the Commandments;</hi> to ſet forth their number, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is ſaid, and their eminency, and therefore they are ſo frequently called in the Scripture, The Commandments of God, diſtinct from the other Laws, which were ſhadowy in the time of the Law of ſhadow.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. [As theſe places of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, beſides many others, do ſhew, <hi>viz. Deut.</hi> 5.31. and 6.11. and 7.11. <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.11. and 11.1. and 30.16. 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 2.3. and 8.58. 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 19.10. <hi>Neh.</hi> 1.7. and 10.29. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the teſtimony of Jeſus in clear Goſpel times, <hi>Rev.</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:151754:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>12.17. <hi>Where,</hi> note, <hi>the dragons war is with the remnant of the Womans ſeed, which keep the Commandments of God, and the Teſtimony of Jeſus;</hi> and again here are they that keep the Commandments of God, and the faith of Jeſus, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.12. And when the man would know what he ſhould do to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, Chriſt told him that he knew the Commandments. A cloud of witneſſes would come in if need were for the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of them. But further obſerve what the Scripture ſaith to their duration; the Pſalmiſt ſaith, <hi>All his Commandments are ſure, they ſtand faſt for ever and ever, and are done in truth and uprightneſſe,</hi> Pſalm 111.7, 8. Note it, all his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which are the works of his hands, as aforeſaid, theſe all ſtand faſt for ever and ever, that is not only in the time of the miniſtration of the letter, which was in a ſenſe for ever, but for ever and ever, that is, under both miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that of the letter, and that of the ſpirit in Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment times, and in the New; and ſearch and ſee if you can find any word that doth ſpeak of any thing that is ſaid to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide, or ſtand faſt for ever and ever, which comes ſhort of the time aforeſaid. And when God hides his face from the houſe of <hi>Jacob,</hi> then is the time that the Teſtimony is bound up, and the Law is ſealed among the diſciples, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 8.16, 17. Clearly relating to the time, that the Jews rejected the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and the diſciples are commanded to make uſe of the Law, as well as the Teſtimony, to try the Doctrines of others by, <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. all which ſhewes the perpetuity of this Law of God, which will further appear if we conſider,</p>
            <p>What our Lord ſaith in <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.17, 18. <hi>Think not that I came to deſtroy the Law or the Prophets, I came not to deſtroy but to fulfil.</hi> But the queſtion will be, what Law this is? To me it appears to be the Law of the Ten Commandments; for theſe reaſons:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, becauſe this comes in as the motive, to provoke his diſciples <hi>to let their lights ſhine in the world, that men might ſee their good works, and glorifie their Father which is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> verſ. 16. Therefore it muſt be ſuch a Law as the doing of it holds forth good works to publique view.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is ſuch a Law as Chriſt profeſſeth he came not to deſtroy; but the Ceremonial Law he did deſtroy in this very
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151754:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſenſe, ſo that none are to be in the practiſe of it; <hi>he blotted out the hand-writing of ordinances that was againſt us, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to us, and took it out of the way, nailing it to his croſſe,</hi> Col. 2.14.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Deſtroying of the Law is here put in direct oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to fulfilling of it; to deſtroy is to take out of the way, or to blot out, as before: but to fulfil the Law, is to do that which is contained in the Law; therefore ſaith Chriſt to <hi>John</hi> (when he went to be baptiſed) <hi>It becometh us to fulfil all righteouſneſs,</hi> (that is, to perform it.) <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.15. and the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>That love is the fulfilling of the Law;</hi> what Law? why this, <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit adultery, Thou ſhalt not kill, Thou ſhalt not ſteal,</hi> and the like, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.8.9. <hi>Love work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no evil to his neighbour, therefore love is the fulfilling of the Law,</hi> verſ. 10. So that to fulfil the Law of the Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments is not to blot them out, or make them void, that were to deſtroy them; which Chriſt came not to do, but on the contrary to do the things contained in them, which he did exactly in his life, and ſo was offered up a Lamb with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpot.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This is ſuch a Law as muſt ſtand in force every jot and title of it till Heaven and Earth paſs away, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5, 19. but Heaven and Earth are not yet paſſed away, therefore this Law ſtands firm: but becauſe it is ſaid in the Text, Till all be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, hence ſome affirm, that all was fulfilled at the death of Chriſt, and this fulfilling of it holds forth the abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of it. But did Heaven and Earth paſs away then? or did Chriſt by his taking upon him all that guilt which was due to us, and by his perfect fulfilling of it in his walk, take us from our obedience? <hi>God forbid;</hi> becauſe Chriſt fulfilled the righteouſneſs of the Law, muſt not we fulfill it?
<note place="margin">Even as <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chippus</hi> was to fulfil his mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, <hi>Col.</hi> 4.17. which would be abſurd to think, that that was to put it to an end.</note> The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, that for this end Chriſt dyed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3, 4. ſaying, <hi>For what the Law could not do, in that it was weak through the fleſh, God ſent forth his ſon in the likeneſs of ſinful fleſh, and for ſin condemned ſin in the fleſh, that the righteouſneſs of the Law might be fulfilled in us, who walk not after the fleſh but after the ſpirit.</hi> But what is the fulfilling of the righteouſneſs of the Law? Firſt to do the righteous things contained in the Law, and in this ſenſe every true believer doth fulfil the Law,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151754:8"/>though his compleatneſs be in Chriſt; for love is the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Law, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.10. ſo that the commanding pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Law is ſuch a juſt meaſure, that every one that loves, acts his part towards the fulfilling of it.</p>
            <p>Laſtly it further appears to be the Ten Commandments, by the uſe Chriſt makes of what he had before aſſerted; <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever therefore ſhall break one of the leaſt of theſe Commendments, and ſhall teach men ſo, ſhall be called leaſt in the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> verſ. 19. that is, foraſmuch as this Law muſt ſtand, till Heaven and Earth paſs: and I came not to deſtroy it; therefore beware of breaking of it, for whoſoever you are that break any any part of it, <hi>and ſhall teach men ſo, you ſhall be called leaſt in the Kingdom of Heaven; but whoſoever ſhall do and teach them, the ſame ſhall be called great in the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> To prevent further miſtakes, he repeateth the Law in many particulars, and gives the ſence, ſhewing how far their righteouſneſs ſhould exceed the righteouſneſs of the Scribes and Phariſees, verſ. 20. By all which it plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that this Law which Chriſt came not to deſtroy, is the Law of the Ten Commandments, or the Laws that were comprehended in them.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The Apoſtle confirmeth and eſtabliſheth this Law af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of Chriſt, as plainly appears <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. the drift of which Chap, is to ſet Jews and Gentiles in a like conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by nature; all breakers of the Law of God, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come guilty before him, verſ. 19. and that therefore no fleſh could be juſtified by the deeds of the Law; the Law being for another purpoſe to convince of ſin, verſ. 20. or to bring ſin to the knowledge; he proves that Jews and Gentiles, circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed and uncircumciſed, are juſtified by and through faith, and not by any Law of works, verſ. 27, 28, 29, 30. But leſt the Gentiles ſhould think, becauſe they could not be juſtified by the works of the Law, that therefore they might look upon the Law as a thing done away or made void: he puts this queſtion to the uncircumciſed Gentiles, <hi>Do we then make void the Law through faith, God forbid; yea we eſtabliſh the Law:</hi> He puts this queſtion out of queſtion, whether the Law be in force to believing Gentiles or no, with a <hi>God forbid;</hi> which ſhews the greatneſs of his zeal againſt ſuch a perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151754:8"/>it being the ſame anſwer which he gives to another groſs queſtion, whether we ſhould continue in ſin that grace <hi>might abound,</hi> and as if that were not enough he adds to it, yea we eſtabliſh <hi>the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. This ſame Apoſtle doth prove, that the Law was in force at the time of his converſion; he ſaith, he had not known ſin but by the Law; he had not known luſt, except the Law had ſaid, Thou ſhalt not covet, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.7. <hi>He was alive without the Law once, but when the Commandment came, ſin revived and he dyed,</hi> verſ. 9. that is, not without the letter of it, for that he had, and did in a great meaſure conform to it, but without powerful convictions for ſin by the Law: and in this ſence when the Commandment came ſin revived, and he dies that before was alive in his own apprehenſion. <hi>For with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Law ſin was dead,</hi> verſ. 8. <hi>and by the Law is the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſin;</hi> and ſin taking occaſion by the Commandment, deceived him, and by it ſlew him. <hi>Wherefore the Law is holy, the Commandment is holy, juſt and good,</hi> verſ. 11.12. not that the holy and juſt Law was made death unto him, God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid; but ſin, that it might appear ſin by this good Law wrought death in him, that by the Commandment ſin might appear exceeding ſinful, verſ. 13. And if ſo, then this Law did not dye with the body of Chriſt; though we are dead to the Law by the body of Chriſt, that we ſhould ſerve in new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſpirit, and not in the oldneſſe of the letter; and that we ſhould be married to another, even him, who is raiſed from the dead; we being dead to that ſpirit of bondage, in whith we were held, that we ſet our obedience to the Law, no longer in the room of Chriſt as our head and husband; Chriſt by his blood, having purchaſed us from that power that the Law had over us by reaſon of ſin. So that our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is not to ſatisfie the Law, as a woman ſerves to pleaſe her husband, that we are dead to: but we are not dead to ſerve in newneſs of ſpirit, in obedience to Chriſt as our husband, verſ. 4, 5, 6. In this ſence the Apoſtle delights in the Law of God, after the inward man, verſ. 22. Though another Law in his members ſtood in great oppoſition to it, verſ. 23. Mind this chap. well, and it will appear ſo plain, that he that runs may read, that the Apoſtle intends no ſuch thing as to take
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151754:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>us from our obedience to the Law, nor yet the abrogating of the Law. But on the contrary,</p>
            <p n="8">8. The ſame Apoſtle urges the Law in the very letter of it unto the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> Chap. 6.1, 2, 3. <hi>Children, ſaith he, obey your Parents, for this is right; Honour thy father and thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which is the firſt Commandment with promiſe.</hi> He proves his exhortation to be right from the Commandment, and he takes notice of the order of the Commandments; it is the firſt Commandment of that ſecond Table, and it hath a promiſe annexed to it, he ſpeaketh in the preſent tenſe: he doth not ſay it was the firſt Commandment, but it is the firſt with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, that thy dayes may be long on the earth; he urges the promiſe to them for their encouragement, and to prevent miſtakes, he ſhews the extent of it, that it was not only to the Jews that they ſhould live long in the land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> but to the Gentiles alſo: therefore the interpretation is large, <hi>that thy dayes may be long on the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>James</hi> gives a full confirmation to what I am treating of, chap. 2.9. He convinces them of ſin by this Law, in having the faith of Jeſus Chriſt with reſpect of perſons, as appears by verſ. 10.11. <hi>For whoſoever ſhall keep the whole Law, and yet offend in one point, he is guilty of all:</hi> he ſhews what Law he means, and how it is that he that offends in one point is guilty of all; becauſe, <hi>He that ſaith, do not commit adultery, ſaith alſo, do not kill; now if thou commit no adultery, yet if thou kill, thou art become a tranſgreſſor of the Law.</hi> And <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>Whoſoever committeth ſin tranſgreſſeth alſo the Law, for ſin is the tranſgreſſionof the Law,</hi> chap. 3.4. and in the next verſe he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains what Law he means; and ſaith, it was ſuch tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that Chriſt was manifeſt to take away: now if this Law of God was done away by the death of Chriſt, ſin could not be a tranſgreſſion of it ſo long after; neither could any be convinced of ſin by it, becauſe it was not: but the Apoſtle ſaith, whoſoever commits ſin, tranſgreſſeth the Law; which ſhews it was in force then, and not only ſo, but that likewiſe it ſhould ſo remain.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Let it be conſidered whether that this opinion that the Law is done away, doth not claſh with redemption it ſelf. The Apoſtle ſtates all men under the Law, and by break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151754:9"/>of it they came under the curſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. And Chriſt was made under the curſe to redeem his people, from under the curſe of the Law, verſ. 13. <hi>that the bleſſing of</hi> Abraham <hi>might come upon the Gentiles through faith,</hi> verſ. 14. Now if we were not under the commanding power, we could not be under the curſe, (for that follows diſobedience) and if ſo then Chriſt was not made a curſe for us; neither can the bleſſing of <hi>Abraham</hi> come upon the Gentiles upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, if the Jews were only under the Law, and under the curſe of it. Chriſt dying to redeem them from the curſe, could not bring the bleſſing of <hi>Abraham</hi> upon the Gentiles. And again the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>that Chriſt was made under the Law, to redeem them that were under the Law, that we might receive the adoption of ſons,</hi> Gal. 4.4, 5. Now if we were not under the Law, we could not be redeemed by Chriſts being under the Law, nor receive the adoption of ſons thereby; but it is manifeſt that every one is under the commanding pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Law, and by nature under the curſe; and Chriſt hath only redeemed his people from the curſe, but that they are redeemed from their obedience to the Law of God: I find no Scripture that ſaith ſo, but on the contrary.</p>
            <p n="11">11. God complaineth of the blindneſs of his ſervants, and of the deafneſs of his meſſengers that he ſent, <hi>Iſay.</hi> 42.19, 20. and their blindneſs and deafneſs appears in this, that they did not hear, nor underſtand Gods deſign in the gift of his Son; that it was not to deſtroy his Law, or to ſlight it, but to magnifie it and make it honorable, verſe 2. Before it was in Tables of ſtone, but now in the fleſhly Tables of the heart; ſervice was done from a ſpirit of bondage, but now from a ſpirit of adoption: and in this ſenſe I conceive the Law is ſaid to be magnified and made honorable, and upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that God is well pleaſed for his righteouſneſs ſake, that is I conceive for his ſons ſake.</p>
            <p n="12">12. This opinion, that the whole Law is aboliſhed, doth pull up true Magiſtracy by the roots; the office of rulers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the puniſhment of evil doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well. But if the ſtatute and judgements be not in force, there is no corporal puniſhment to be inflicted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any though theeves, murderers, or the like; and ſo there
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151754:10"/>is no room for the Magiſterial power at all, but men are left in this reſpect as the beaſts of the field, to ſhift one among an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other as well as they can. But the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>The Law is made for the Lawleſs and diſobedient, for ungodly and for ſinners, for unholy and prophane, for murderers of fathers, and murderers of mothers, for man-flayers,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.9, 10. Now this is the Law of penalties, that's manifeſt in that it is ſaid, it was not made for a righteous man, but the Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments were for the righteous: for the Pſalmiſt ſaith, <hi>Oh how I love thy Law, it is my meditation all the day,</hi> Pſalm. 119.97. <hi>Make me to go in the path of thy Commandments, for therein do I delight,</hi> verſ. 35.</p>
            <p>And how ſhall we have Governers as at the firſt, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers as at the beginning, <hi>Iſay.</hi> 1.26. if they have no Law to govern by; If any ſay we ſhall have Laws from Chriſt, and ſhall not need thoſe Laws that were for the Common-wealth of Iſrael: to that I anſwer, I know no word of God that doth give us ground to believe for any other Laws or Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, then what we have; and ſuppoſe that God ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive his work in this nation, and bring his enemies under, and put opportunity into the hands of his Saints, to chuſe men fearing God and hating covetouſneſſe, to rule the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion while the Lambs army march on. What could they do if the Scripture were not their Statute-book, if they ſhould turn Law-makers, would not that be their ſin, there being no Warrant in the Scripture for it? And would it not bring all into confuſion again, and make another Babel? For the great queſtion which is to be reſolved in the latter dayes, will be, Who is our Statute-maker? Which the Saints put out of queſtion, <hi>Iſay.</hi> 33.22. <hi>The Lord is our Judge, the Lord is our Statute-maker, the Lord is our King, he will ſave us,</hi> (and not King <hi>Omri</hi> with his Statutes, <hi>Mic.</hi> 6.16.) And when the Saints come to own this truth in good earneſt, their oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits tacklings will be looſed, <hi>they ſhall neither ſtrengthen their maſt, nor ſpread their ſailes,</hi> verſ. 23. and <hi>Malachi</hi> tells us, what Laws our King hath made, which the Saints are to own, when the day of the Lord burns as an oven all the proud, and the Sun of righteonſneſs ariſes upon all that fear him, when they ſhall tread down the wicked with ſo much
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151754:10"/>eaſe, that they ſhall be as aſhes under the ſoles of their feet, ſo that it ſhall be counted the Lords doings. And in the day that the Lord ſhall do this, <hi>Remember ye the Law of</hi> Moſes <hi>my ſervant, which I commanded unto him in</hi> Horeb <hi>for all Iſrael with the Statutes and judgements,</hi> Chap. 4.3, 4.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now endeavour to anſwer ſome objections which are uſually brought againſt this truth, though ſeveral of them are partly anſwered in the grounds aforementioned; I ſhall therefore ſay the leſs, and begin to ſpeak ſomething to that Scripture in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. on which the objecters do chiefly build their perſwaſion, and indeed at the firſt glance thereon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out comparing of it with other Scriptures, it hath more co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour for ſuch a purpoſe then all the Scriptures that ever I heard brought: from which Scripture this is objected, That the Ten Commandments were the miniſtration of death and of the letter, and are done away.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> That they were the miniſtration of death and of the letter is granted, for the Scripture ſaith ſo, but the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture doth not ſay they are done away: as will appear, if we conſider the drift of the Apoſtle, he endeavoureth to ſhew the difference between the miniſtration of the ſpirit and of the letter, verſ. 6. the one being a bare reading of the Law, from which no life was communicated to thoſe that heard it, verſ. 14, 15. and in verſ. 9. the Apoſtle calls it <hi>the miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of condemnation,</hi> that is, it lays open ſin, and the curſe for ſin, but it is the Goſpel miniſtration which holds forth juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and ſtrength againſt ſin; not that the Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments in themſelves were death to any. <hi>God forbid.</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaith in <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.13. <hi>But ſin when it is finiſhed brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth forth death,</hi> and the Commandements preach death to the tranſgreſſers of them, ſo that they are called the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of death and condemnation, becauſe man hath bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them, and ſo is under the curſe of them, which Chriſt hath delivered believers from, 3.13. and the miniſtration of it is really done away, that is, as I ſaid before, The read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Law by a Typical prieſthood, which the Jews would have ſet up in the room and place of the miniſtration of the ſpirit: and whereas they lived under the hearing of the bare letter of the Law, which gave no ſtrength to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151754:11"/>we live under the hearing of the Goſpel, which is ſpirit and life, <hi>John</hi> 6.36. But that the matter of the Law or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding power of it ſhould be done away, this Scripture doth not in the leaſt prove, but it is uſed in the hand of the ſpirit to convince of ſin. This the ſame Apoſtle proves <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.7. <hi>Who,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>had not known ſin but by the Law, he had not known luſt except the Law had ſaid thou ſhalt not covet:</hi> this will appear evident if you conſider the 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14. verſes of this Chap.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. Another Scripture is frequently urged, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.37. <hi>A Prophet ſhall the Lord your God raiſe up unto you of your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, like unto me, him ſhall you hear.</hi> From which it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that we are to hearken only to Chriſt, and not to <hi>Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If by hearing of Chriſt you mean, hearing only what he ſpake with his own lips when he was on earth, then we are not to hear his Apoſtles; but if you mean by hearing of him is to hear what he ſpake upon earth, and what he ſpake by his ſpirit in his Apoſtles, then why are we not to hear what he ſpake by his ſpirit to his Prophets: <hi>ſeeing we are built upon the foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets, Chriſt being the chief Corner-ſtone, Epheſians</hi> 21.20. And if ſuch who are of this perſwaſion, would be true to their principle to hear Chriſt, hear him what he ſaith, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.31. <hi>They have</hi> Moſes <hi>and the Prophets let them hear them. For if they will not believe</hi> Moſes <hi>and the Prophets they will not believe, though one riſe from the dead.</hi> And he counſels to keep the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.17, 18. and reproves for the breach of them; as alſo for the making of them void by traditions, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.6. as might be made appear by many other Scriptures. Therefore there is nothing of weight in this objection to ſhake the thing aſſerted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 3. <hi>Moſes</hi> was faithful over his houſe as a ſervant, ſo Chriſt is faithful over his houſe as a ſon. Now if Chriſt hath not given us all the Laws that we are to obſerve, this is to make Chriſt leſs faithful then <hi>Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Doubtleſſe Chriſt as a ſon is faithful over his houſe, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was faithful over his houſe as a ſervant. But we are to conſider, what was <hi>Moſes</hi> his houſe, and what is Chriſts
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151754:11"/>houſe; <hi>Moſes</hi> his houſe, I conceive, was the Tabernacle: his faithfulneſs did appear, in that he did all things according to the pattern ſhewed to him in the mount. Chriſts houſe are the Saints <hi>the true Tabernacle which the Lord hath pitched and not man,</hi> Heb. 8.2, 5. of which the other was a ſhadow. And as <hi>Moſes</hi> as a ſervant gave forth ordinances for his houſe, ſo Chriſt as a ſon hath given out ordinances for his houſe: but the Ten Commandments are a Law which belongs to men as they are men, though they be no part of Chriſts houſe, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as before is proved, the Law written in their very hearts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 4. But when certain of the Sect of the Phariſees a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe, and ſaid it was needful to be circumciſed, and keep the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Apoſtle proves them to be tempters of God, in putting a yoke upon the neck of the diſciples, which they nor their Fathers were able to bear, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.5, 10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Are the Ten Commandments ſuch a yoke, as is not to be born? Is it a yoke to have no other God but Jehovah, and to abſtain from murder, theft, adultery, and the like? For ſo it muſt be, if you judge that the whole Law is here ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But the thing in difference here is, whether ſuch and ſuch laws are to be kept or no? and the ſtreſs that is laid upon the keeping of them, namely the preſſing of them as things without which they could not be ſaved, as verſ. 1. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle in anſwer to this, ſhews that the Gentiles had received the Gospel, and did believe, God having gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to them the Holy Ghoſt, and put no difference between them and the Jews, purifying their hearts by faith, verſ. 7, 8, 9. and that through the grace of Jeſus Chriſt both ſews and Gentiles ſhould be ſaved, verſ. 11. and as the Apoſtle oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the keeping of theſe Laws for ſuch a purpoſe as to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thereby, ſo the bare keeping of them is forbidden: and therefore ſaith <hi>James</hi> ver. 19, 20. <hi>My ſentence is that we trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble not them which from among the Gentiles are turned unto God, but that we write unto them that they abſtain from pollutions of Idols, and from fornication, from things ſtrangled and from blood.</hi> So that the Apoſtles judgement is, that the Gentiles ſhould keep ſome part of the Law. And therefore the queſtion was not, Whether any part of the Law ſhould be kept? and the reaſon ſeems to be in verſ. 20. why they would write no
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151754:12"/>more, <hi>for Moſes of old time hath in every City them that preach him, being read in the Synagogue ever Sabbath day.</hi> So the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Elders write verſ. 24. <hi>For as much as we have heard, that certain men that went out from us have troubled you with words ſubverting your ſouls, ſaying you muſt be circumciſed and keep the Law, to whom we gave no ſuch Commandment.</hi> Now can we be ſo groſs as to think, that is ſubverting mens ſouls, and contrary to the commandments of the Apoſtles and El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, to bid them love the Lord their God with all their hearts, and with all their ſtrength, and to worſhip him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and not take his name in vain, and the like? for this is to keep the Law. But the difference was about other Laws as well as circumciſion, and they are as really forbid to keep them, as they are forbid circumciſion: and therefore it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the Law of the Ten Commandments, but the Law of ſhadows, as is manifeſt, Chap. 21. when <hi>Paul</hi> came to <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> the brethren told him, that it was reported, that he taught all the Jews which were among the Gentiles to forſake <hi>Moſes, ſaying, that they ought not to circumciſe their children, neither to walk after the cuſtomes,</hi> verſ. 21. therefore they counſel <hi>Paul</hi> to purifie himſelf with ſome others, that it might be ſeen that he walked orderly and kept the Law, verſ. 24. <hi>But as touching the Gentiles which believe we have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and concluded that they obſerve no ſuch things,</hi> verſ. 25. ſo that it's very clear that 'tis circumciſion and the cuſtomes that's here called the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> which the Gentiles were commanded not to keep, but to think the Gentiles ſhould be forbidden to keep that Law of God that was written in their natures, is abominable, and contrary both to Scripture and reaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 5. But the Scripture ſaith, Caſt out the Bond-woman with her ſon, for the ſon of the Bond-woman ſhall not be heir with the ſon of the Free-woman, which Bond-woman was an Allegory of the Covenant from mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> and therefore to be caſt out.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Apoſtle is here ſhewing how impoſſible it is for works and grace to ſtand together in point of juſtification; for this people were ſeeking to be juſtified by the works of the Law. He ſhews the difference betwixt the two Covenants,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151754:12"/>one of works gendering to bondage, <hi>the righteouſneſs of the Law being this, that the man that doth theſe things ſhould live in them,</hi> Rom. 10.5. the other of grace or free promiſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reſpect to mans righteouſneſs: he ſhews the ſons of the Covenants are like unto their mothers; the ſons of the one Covenant are born after the fleſh, the ſons of the other by promiſe, and that thoſe that are born after the fleſh, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute thoſe that are born after the ſpirit. Nevertheleſs what ſaith the Scripture? <hi>Caſt out the Bond-woman and her ſon; For the ſon of the Bond-woman ſhall not be heir with the ſon of the Free-woman.</hi> That is, The Covenant of works with thoſe that ſeek to be juſtified thereby, <hi>Chriſt being the end of the Law for righteouſneſs to every one that believeth,</hi> Rom. 10.4. But if we ſhould underſtand the Ten Commandments in themſelves, to be the Bond-woman, then it is impoſſible for them that keep them to be heires or children of the promiſe, but they muſt be caſt out as children of the Bond-woman, which is very erronious, and contrary to the current of Scriptures. For <hi>the doers of the Law are juſtified before God,</hi> Rom. 2.13. though not for doing. And mark how the Apoſtle forbids this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.31. <hi>Do we then make void the Law through faith? God forbid. Shall we continue in ſin or tranſgreſs the Law, that grace may abound? God forbid,</hi> Rom. 6. <hi>Is the Law ſin? God forbid,</hi> Rom. 7.7. <hi>Was the Law which was good made death unto me? God forbid,</hi> 13. <hi>Shall we tranſgreſs the Law becauſe we are not under the condemning power of it?</hi> (Chriſt having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed us from it) <hi>God forbid,</hi> Rom. 6.15. Certainly the Scripture did foreſee how apt men would be to ſlight and make void the Law of God under ſpecious pretences, as their being believers, and Gentiles which had not the Law given to them, but that they are under grace and the like. <hi>But if the uncircumciſion keep the righteouſneſſe of the Law, ſhall not his uncircumciſion be counted for circumciſion.</hi> Rom. 2.26.</p>
            <p>Conſider theſe Queres, 1. If the whole Law was done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by the death of Chriſt, why did the Apoſtle ſpend ſo much time to prove that by the works of the Law none could be juſtified, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. ſeeing there was no Law to work upon? Had it not been a nearer way to have told them that the Law was aboliſhed?</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:151754:13"/>
            <p n="2">2. If the whole Law was done away at the death of Chriſt, how can any part of it be now in force? If it be ſaid it is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a new account, ſhew me any one Law that Chriſt hath once deſtroyed, and again revived; ſeeing the Apoſtle ſaith if he ſhould build again the things that he deſtroyed, he ſhould make himſelf a tranſgreſſor, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.14.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What Scripture is it that proves that we have any one of the Ten Commandments given out upon a new account?</p>
            <p n="4">4. If the whole Law be done away, what Law is there for the puniſhment of evil doers, theeves, murderers, and the like?</p>
            <p n="5">5. If the Ten Commandments were to be aboliſhed, how is it that the Lord hath annexed ſo many great and precious promiſes unto the keeping of them, and delighting in them? as in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.1, 2, 3, 4. and many other places which do of right belong unto ſuch as keep the Commandements, <hi>Rev.</hi> 27.14.</p>
            <p n="6">6. How is it that the Apoſtle ſaith, the Law is good if a man uſe it lawfully, 1 <hi>Tim,</hi> 1 8. if at the ſame time there was no Low?</p>
            <p n="7">7. If the Law was done away at the death of Chriſt, when was it given again upon a new account? If before his death in the 5. of <hi>Matth.</hi> then how is it that the Law that was given on <hi>Sinai</hi> ſtood in force till his death? Could they ſtand both in force at once. If not till after the death of Chriſt, then when was it given out? ſeeing we find not any of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements ſo much as mentioned for a long time after the death of Chriſt. Can we think the Saints and the world were left without Law?</p>
            <p n="8">8. How is it that we contend for Governors as at the firſt, and Counſellers as at the beginning? ſeeing there is no Law for them to rule and govern by, if this doctrine be true that the whole Law is done away?</p>
            <p>Thus I have endeavoured in a weak meaſure to prove that the Ten Commandments are not only in force to unbelievers, but alſo to believers. But believers are not under the Law, ſo as to be juſtified or condemned by it; not under it as a Covenant of works and miniſtration of death, but under it as it's a righteous rule of life, a holy, juſt and good Law, ſo
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151754:13"/>they are under it, and do delight in it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.22. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.70, 72, 97. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is time for the Lord to work, for they have made void thy thy Law.</hi> Pſal. 119.122.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore I love thy Commandments above Gold, yea above fine Gold,</hi> verſ. 127.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore I eſteem all thy precepts concerning all things to be right, and I hate every falſe way,</hi> verſ. 128.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <head>The ſeventh day is the Sabbath.</head>
            <p>NOw if the Ten Commandments be in force every jot and title of them, it muſt neceſſarily follow that the Seventh day is the Sabbath, and is to be obſerved according to the commandment. But becauſe there is much oppoſition againſt this truth, I ſhall offer ſomething in particular to it, which may tend to the clearing of it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it was inſtituted by God before the fall of man, as appears in <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.31. <hi>And God ſaw every thing that he had made, and behold it was very good.</hi> But when men had ſinned, God changes his voice, and then the ground is curſed for his ſake, Chap. 3.17. Further, God was ſix dayes upon his work of creation, and reſted not until the ſeventh day: now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the end of the ſixt day and the beginning of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, there is no interval or ſpace of time, Chap. 1.31. Chap. 2.2. then why ſhould it be thought that the Sabbath was a ſhadow to hold forth reſt by faith in Chriſt, ſeeing <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> had not ſinned, and ſo had no need of a Saviour? and why ſhould we run into ſuch imaginations, concerning the cauſe of Gods inſtituting the Sabbath, ſeeing God ſo plainly declareth it himſelf? namely, that <hi>He bleſſed the ſeventh day and ſanctified it, becauſe that in it he reſted from all his works which God created and made,</hi> Chap. 2.3.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The reaſon that the Lord gives when he commanded the obſervation of the ſeventh day is, as before, <hi>becauſe that in ſix dayes the Lord made Heaven and Earth, the Sea, and all that in them is, and reſted the ſeventh day, wherefore the Lord bleſſed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151754:14"/>the Sabbath day and hallowed it,</hi> Exod. 20.11. and it is as a motive to provoke man to follow the Lords example from the beginning both in work and reſt. <hi>Six dayes,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>thou ſhalt labour and do all thy work, but the ſeventh day is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God, in it thou ſhalt do no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of works.</hi> And if thou wouldſt know a reaſon, why thou ſhouldſt do ſo, it is becauſe I the Lord thy God did ſo. And truly to me its clear that one main reaſon, why the Lord took ſo much time as ſix dayes to create all things in, and reſted the ſeventh day, was to ſhew man an example, and what he ought to do. Doubtleſs God could have made all things in a moment, but ſix dayes he works, and reſts the ſeventh day, that man might do the ſame, and thereby not only hold forth the creating power of God, and the method that he was pleaſed to take in the creation, but alſo his great mercy in inſtructing and commanding man to work ſix dayes, and reſt the ſeventh that he might be refreſhed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It plainly appears, that this inſtitution was in force and to be obſerved from the beginning, though no mention is made of the Patriarks obſerving of it, no more then of their ſacrificings and doing many other things, which is judged they did, notwithſtanding we hear nothing of them. But conſider God reſted the ſeventh day and ſanctified it: now to prophane that which God ſanctifies doubtleſs is a ſin; and had they done ſervile work upon the Sabbath they had prophaned it, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 13.16, 17. and what the Lord ſaid to <hi>Peter</hi> in another caſe, may be rightly ſaid in this, <hi>(viz.) What God hath ſanctified that call not thou common or unclean,</hi> Act. 10.15. and the Lord when he gives forth this command, ſaith, <hi>Remember the Sabbath,</hi> to note the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of it, and the antiquity of it, it being no new thing but from the beginning, and that the Lord urges in verſe 11. as the cauſe why it was to be obſerved. Iſrael obſerved the Sabbath before the giving of the Law on mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> as appears <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.23, 25, 26. But mark what <hi>Nehemiah</hi> ſaith to this, Chap. 9.13. <hi>Thou cameſt down alſo upon mount Sinai, and ſpeakeſt with them from Heaven, and gaveſt them right judgements, and true Laws, good Statutes and Commandments, and madeſt known alſo unto them thy holy Sabbath,</hi> verſ. 14.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151754:14"/>Mark, this commandment is ſingled out from all the reſt, and is ſaid to be made known to them, which ſhews it was in being before, though its probable they might loſe the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of it, by reaſon of their hard bondage in Egypt; but however its plain that they had need of the knowledge of the Sabbath, and God makes it known unto them, and Chriſt leads us plainly to the firſt inſtitution of it, <hi>The Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath</hi> ſaith he, <hi>was made for man, and not man for the Sabbath.</hi> He points to the making of it and for whom it was made, not for the Jews only as Jews but for man before any diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction was of Jew &amp; Gentile; and in that it was made for that man which was the publique perſon or repreſentative of whole mankind it was made for all men, <hi>Adam</hi> ſtanding as a publique perſon before his fall.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Our Lord Jeſus doth ſhew the true end of Gods gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Sabbath, and alſo how it ought to be kept, and ſhews the Phariſees their miſtake in the obſervation of it, they being ſo rigid that they would not ſuffer good works and works of mercy to be done, though there were neceſſity for the doing of them: as will appear if we conſider theſe Scriptures following; The Phariſees ask Chriſt, <hi>If it were lawful to heal on the Sabbath day? that they might accuſe him,</hi> Matth. 12.10. and his anſwer is this, <hi>What man is there among you that ſhall have one ſheep, and if it fall into a pit on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day will he not lay hold on it and lift it out?</hi> verſ. 11. <hi>How much then is a man better then a ſheep? wherefore it is lawful to do well on the Sabbath dayes,</hi> verſ. 12. Mark. 34. Again the Phariſees told Chriſt that his diſciples did that which was not lawful, becauſe they pull the ears of Corn upon the Sabbath day, <hi>Mark.</hi> 2.24. But mind the anſwer of Chriſt, <hi>Have ye not read what David did when he was an hungry and had need, how he entred into the houſe of God, and did eat the Shew-bread, which is not lawful for any to eat but the Prieſts?</hi> ver. 25.26. Matth. 12.3, 4. <hi>Or have ye not read in the Law, that the Prieſts in the Temple prophane the Sabbath dayes and are blameleſs?</hi> verſ. 5. It was not unlawful to pluck the ears of Corn when they went through their neighbours field, for that they might do by the Law of God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.25. and that the Phariſees knew very well; but they thought it was
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151754:15"/>unlawful becauſe they did it upon the Sabbath day: but mark the anſwer of Chriſt how he cleared the diſciples, it was unlawful for <hi>David</hi> to eat the Shew-bread, but he was an hungry and had need, and therefore to be excuſed; for if the diſciples had puld the ears of Corn (when they had no need) upon the Sabbath day, it had been doing of needleſſe work, and ſo had been unlawful: but the Text ſaith they were an hungry, therefore they might do it, it being a work of mercy as <hi>Davids</hi> was; and the ſame may be ſaid of the Prieſts prophaning the Sabbath, who notwithſtanding are ſaid to be blameleſſe, their preparing the ſacrifices was alow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which work in it ſelf would have been counted a ſervile work, but that it was for ſuch a merciful end, <hi>(viz,)</hi> the ſins of the people: therefore ſaith Chriſt, <hi>had ye known what this meaneth I will have mercy and not ſacrifice, you would not have condemned the guiltleſs,</hi> verſ. 7. Cleerly proving that the Sabbath was to be obſerved (but not ſo as to break another command, to neglect mercy which the Phariſees would do, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23 23.) and that his diſciples in having mercy to their bodies were no Sabbath-breakers.</p>
            <p>Further obſerve what Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Mark.</hi> 2.27. <hi>The Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath was made for man, and not man for the Sabbath;</hi> the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees made themſelves ſlaves and bond-men, by making the Sabbath a yoak (whereas it ſhould have been a delight, <hi>Iſay.</hi> 58.13.) by ſuperſtitious outſide performances, as though man had been made for the Sabbath; but Chriſt tells them it was made for man, that is, for the good and benefit of man that man might reſt from his own labours and be refreſhed, [as the Lord was, <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.17.] and thus you ſee how clearly our Lord hath given the ſenſe of this Law: it is lawful to do well upon the Sabbath day, to viſite the ſick and to heal them, and to do works of mercy to our own and others bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, the Sabbath being made for man.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Jeſus Chriſt declares himſelf to be Lord even of the Sabbath day, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.8. and he takes his title thus, the Sabbath, ſaith he, was made for man, and not man for the Sabbath, therefore the ſon of man is Lord even of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day, <hi>Mark</hi> 2.27. and here ſeems to be two things from whence Chriſt takes this title: Firſt, the Sabbath was made
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151754:15"/>for man, that is as before was ſaid,
<note place="margin">Chriſt being Lord of the Sabbath doth no more make it void then his being Lord of the Supper, and Lord of the Harveſt, doth make the Supper and the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt void.</note> for <hi>Adam</hi> and ſo for all men, being made for him before his fall; now Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſon of man, the chief man or ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> the man of Gods right hand, the heir of all things is of right Lord even of the Sabbath. 2. The Sabbath was made for man, that is, for the good of man and in mercy to man, as is ſaid before, therefore Chriſt being the Author of all good, the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of all mercy, he is Lord of it and therefore Chriſt doth not ſlight the Sabbath (as ſome do imagine) by ſaying he is Lord of it, as though he were not to keep it, or that his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent were to change it; that were to ſtrip himſelf of his title, or elſe to entitule himſelf Lord of that which was not: but in that it is ſaid Chriſt is Lord of the Sabbath, it proves the Sabbath to be in force, as Chriſt proves the reſurrection, <hi>Mark.</hi> 12.26, 27. <hi>I am the God of Abraham, the God of Iſaac, the God of Jacob: he is not the God of the dead but of the living;</hi> ſo Chriſt is Lord of the Sabbath day, he is not Lord of dead Types, and ſhadows or of that which is not in being, but he is Lord of the lively Oracles, of which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sabbath is one, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.38.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But did not Chriſt break the Sabbath and teach men ſo to do in bidding the impotent man take up his bed and walk, it being unlawful to carry a burthen upon the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Scribes and Phariſees ſaid ſo indeed, and that his bed was a burthen, but they were very unfit Judges, they being ignorant of the right obſerving of the Sabbath, and ſought likewiſe to take advantage againſt Chriſt in his words and actions; their ſaying the mans bed was a burthen, and that it was unlawful for him to carry it doth prove no more that ſo it was, then their ſaying that the diſciples brake the Sabbath in plucking the ears of Corn, and Chriſt in healing the diſeaſed: but was not this a work of mercy, the man ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving lien lame ſo long in the porch now being cured? Was it not meet that he ſhould be releaſed from the place, and take his bed with him to lye upon at night? for its likely he had no other. And who can ſay that his bed was a burthen, for in ſome Countries that which they call their bed is no hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vier then a good Cloak or Coat; but conſider what groſſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151754:16"/>wickedneſſe naturally flows from this opinion. The objecters themſelves and all muſt acknowledge that the whole Law was in force till the death of Chriſt, the very ſhadows till he nailed them to his Croſs; then the fourth Commandment doubtleſſe was in full force: now to ſay that Chriſt brake it, and taught men ſo, is to ſay, Chriſt ſinned and taught men to ſin; for ſin is the tranſgreſſion of the Law, and this roots up redemption by Chriſt; for if Chriſt was a ſinner he could not be a Saviour, he had not been a meet-offering for the ſins of others if he had been a ſinner himſelf; but he was offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up a Lamb without ſpot, [<hi>Heb.</hi> 7.26. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19.] and was made ſin for us, that knew no ſin, [2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.2.] And therefore this objection is ſo groſs that every ſincere heart that ſees the tendency of it will not touch it; and indeed I had not mentioned it here, but that many through weakneſs have taken it up as a ſufficient ground to prove the making void the Sabbath, for want of looking into the bottom of it.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Another ground to prove the Sabbath yet to be in force may be taken from the words of Chriſt to his diſciples, <hi>Matt.</hi> 24.20. <hi>But pray ye that your flight be not in winter, nor on the Sabbath day;</hi> which is part of the anſwer Chriſt gave them when they came privately to him to ask him when the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Temple ſhould be, the ſignes of his coming and the end of the world. It is generally conceived that this part of Chriſts anſwer, relates to the deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and indeed that is the ſhorteſt time that can be thought it relates unto, as doth appear by the queſtion which was asked him; but ſuppoſe it ſo, doth it not plainly appear from hence, that the Sabbath was to remain in full force, after the death of Chriſt? The deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> being about 40. years after the death of Chriſt, and yet he commands his diſciples to pray that their flight be not in the winter, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the Sabbath day; now can we think that Chriſt would lay ſuch a foundation for ſuperſtition, as though the Sabbath was to be at the ruin of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> when it was to ceaſe at his death: or can we think-that Chriſt would teach his diſciples to pray falſe, or to pray that their flight ſhould not be on the Sabbath, when indeed there was to be no Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath; this is groſs to imagine, but as ſure as winter was to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151754:16"/>remain winter, ſo the Sabbath was to remain the Sabbath, and if their flight had been upon it, it would have been the more tedious, it being a day of reſt and refreſhment, to them wherein they uſed to rejoyce and praiſe the Lord, as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by that Pſalm or ſong for the Sabbath day, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 92. But although this Scripture looks to the deſtruction of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> yet I conceive it looks further, even to that diſtreſs that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhall be in at the ſecond coming of Chriſt, and that for theſe reaſons;</p>
            <p>Firſt, thoſe things that Chriſt ſpake of, were accompliſhed in a meaſure in the Apoſtles dayes, and yet they are not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly fulfilled; for inſtance, Chriſt told his diſciples that they ſhould be delivered up to be killed, and they ſhould be hated of all Nations for his name ſake; this was in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles dayes and hath been ſince, and falſe Prophets did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe then, and ſo they have ſince then, verſ. 4.11. So that thoſe things which Chriſt ſpake lookt to ſeveral times, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I conceive he ſaith in verſ. 24. <hi>Verily I ſay unto you this generation ſhall not paſſe till all theſe things be fulfilled;</hi> and ſo I judge, what he ſpake concerning <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> had not only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to that deſtruction that came upon it in that generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but alſo to that great calamity that ſhould be upon it in the laſt dayes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This will more plainly appear, if we conſider the words of Chriſt, <hi>But pray ye that your flight be not in the winter nor on the Sabbath day, for then ſhall be great tribulation, ſuch as was not ſince the beginning of the world to this time, no nor ever ſhall be,</hi> ver. 21. Now with this compare, <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.2. <hi>For I will gather all nations againſt Jeruſalem to battle, and the City ſhall be taken, and the houſes rifled, and the women raviſhed.</hi> and at the 2. verſe it is ſaid, <hi>then ſhall the Lord go forth and fight againſt thoſe nations as when he fought in the day of battle, and his feet ſhall ſtand in that day upon the mount of Olives,</hi> verſ. 4. With this compare, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. <hi>And at that time ſhall Michael ſtand up the great Prince which ſtandeth for the children of thy people, and there ſhall be a time of trouble ſuch as never was ſince there was a nation even to that ſame time, and at that time thy people ſhall be delivered, every one that ſhall be found written in the book, and many of them that ſleep in the duſt ſhall
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151754:17"/>awake, ſome to everlaſting life, &amp; ſome to ſhame &amp; contempt,</hi> ver. 2. Now if that deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> produced ſuch great trouble as never was, nor ever ſhould be again; how is it that there ſhall be ſuch great trouble as never was ſince there was a nation? when <hi>Michael</hi> ſtands up to deliver his people every one that is written in the book, and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is taken and the houſes rifled, and women raviſhed, when the Lord comes forth to fight againſt thoſe nations, and his feet ſhall ſtand upon the mount of Olives, according to that in <hi>Acts</hi> 1.11. <hi>So ſhall he come in like manner as ye have ſeen him go into Heaven,</hi> and when the ſeventh Angel poures out his vial, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.17, 18. which time I conceive is one and the ſame with that in <hi>Zach.</hi> and <hi>Dan.</hi> and the Angel is <hi>Michael</hi> the great Prince which <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeaks of, whoſe feet ſhall ſtand upon the mount of Olives, then is the time of great trouble, and ſuch an earth-quake as was not ſince men were upon the face of the earth ſo mighty an earth-quake and ſo great; ſo that to me it appears that theſe three Scriptures do coreſpond with the words of Chriſt pointing out the ſame time: and if ſo then the Sabbath ſhall remain till the coming of Chriſt, and ſo ſhall ſtand <hi>till Heaven and Earth paſse,</hi> according to that in <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. and <hi>for ever and ever,</hi> according to that in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.8. and the deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſeems to be a Type of that great deſtruction that ſhall be at Chriſts appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: and as <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was taken when ſome from all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were gathered together, as hiſtory reports, and on the Sabbath day it was deſtroyed; ſo it appears that the ſtrength of the Saints will be gathered together to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> becauſe all Nations will gather againſt it, and <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> ſtraights will be upon the Sabbath day, as ſeems to appear by the words of Chriſt, for then, ſaith he, ſhall be great tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch as never was; (then when,) why when their flight ſhall be upon the Sabbath day, and this great tribulation is when <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhall be taken, the houſes rifled, and the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men raviſhed, as was ſaid before; <hi>at which time Michael ſhall ſtand up and fight againſt thoſe Nations, as when he fought in the day of battle, and the ſlain of the Lord ſhall be many, even from one end of the earth even to the other,</hi> Jer. 25.31, 32, 33. <hi>and the mount of Olives ſhall cleave in the midſt thereof,</hi> Zach.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151754:17"/>14.4. <hi>and there ſhall be a very great valley, unto which the Saints ſhall flee,</hi> verſ. 5. then ſhall the Sabbath be ſwallowed up in the great Sabbath or thouſand years, that glorious and holy reſt which the Saints ſhall enter into and live and reign with Chriſt a thouſand years, verſ. 9. and 20. <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.4.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Another ground is taken from the practiſe of Chriſts diſciples after his death, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.5, 6. <hi>And they returned and prepared ſpices and oyntments, and reſted the Sabbath day ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Commandment.</hi> Some ſay if we do obſerve the Sabbath we muſt do all thoſe ſacrifices which the Jews did upon it, but at this time the vail of the Temple was rent in twain from the top to the bottom, and the ſhadows were done away by the body of Chriſt, and yet they kept the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, and not through fear or ignorance, but according to the Commandment, which is to reſt from their labours, and ſo they did; for the Text ſaith, <hi>they returned and reſted,</hi> there is no ſacrifice expreſſed in the Commandment. <hi>The ſtranger and the cattle was to reſt the Sabbath,</hi> Exo. 20.10. ſo that the Sabbath was commanded and obſerved before any of thoſe ſacrifices were commanded to be offered upon it, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Jews did ſuch ſervice upon the Sabbath day as they were a typical people, it doth not follow that this was any part of the Commandment, and therefore we are to reſt as thoſe diſciples did, according to the Commandment: and it is remarkable that the Holy Ghoſt ſhould leave this upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, which would not have been I am perſwaded, had the Sabbath then been aboliſht; he doth not only ſay they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned and reſted the Sabbath day, but to prevent all miſtakes leaſt it ſhould be thought they did it ignorantly or ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, or for fear of the Jews, he ſaith they did it groundedly (that is) according to the commandment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But the diſciples were met together upon the firſt day of the week, and Chriſt appeared to them, <hi>John</hi> 20.9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true they were aſſembled together on the ſame day at even being the firſt day of the week, and the door ſhut, and the cauſe is laid down why ſo they were; namely for fear of the Jews: and ſome of the diſciples, as I ſaid before, kept the Sabbath the day before, and I think we cannot reaſonably imagine but thoſe did that were together on the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151754:18"/>firſt day, for they did frequently correſpond together, that's manifeſt; but what doth their being together on the firſt day at even, and Chriſts appearing to them prove for the obſervation of the firſt day, more then his appearing to them eight days after, and his appearing to them the third time early in the morning when they were a fiſhing, <hi>Joh.</hi> 24.4 5. for the obſervation of theſe dayes? It was neceſſary that Chriſt ſhould appear to his diſciples on the firſt day of the week, that his word might be fulfilled of his ariſing the third day, and that they might boldly witneſs the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But the diſciples came together on the firſt day of the week, and did break bread, and <hi>Paul</hi> taught unto them, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is all the meeting or preaching that ever we find was upon the firſt day, except the diſciples being toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for fear of the Jews, mentioned before that meeting, was at evening; ſo this ſeems to be, becauſe when they came to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether <hi>Paul</hi> preached with them and continued his ſpeech un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til midnight; it is not likely then that they obſerved the day and came together in the morning, ſeeing he continued his ſpeech ſo long. And ſecondly, as we have the cauſe of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples being together with their doors ſhut, ſo we have the cauſe of this meeting; <hi>Paul</hi> was ready to depart on the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, verſ. 7. upon an extraordinary occaſion, <hi>Paul</hi> having many things to communicate to them, as appears by his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing with them till midnight, and talking till break of day, verſ. 11. But that which makes the Objecters lay ſuch ſtreſs upon this Text, is becauſe the diſciples came together to break bread, which they judge to be the Lords Supper. Suppoſe it were ſo, what doth this make for the obſervation of the firſt day, more then Chriſts firſt inſtituting the ſupper upon the fifth day of the week (as is generally conceived,) doth make for the obſervation of it? But there is no proof that this was the Supper of the Lord that they came to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of, but it ſeems to be ſuch breaking of bread as the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin of ſome Bibles refers unto. <hi>Acts</hi> the 2.46. <hi>They continued dayly with one accord in the Temple, and breaking bread from houſe to houſe, did eat their meat with gladneſſe of heart.</hi> (So <hi>Luc.</hi> 24.30 35.) And it is explained what breaking of bread it
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151754:18"/>was verſ. 11. where it is ſaid when he was come up again and had broken bread and eaten, and talked a good while till break of the day he departed: here is eating and talking, it is not ſolemnized as the Supper of the Lord: But ſome would have this common breaking of bread, and the other in verſe 7. to be the Supper; it is very unlikely that here ſhould be two ſorts of breaking of bread at one time by the ſame perſons, and yet nothing ſpoke diſtinctly by which we might know the one from the other, ſo that the moſt that can be ſaid, is but a ſuppoſition; it cannot be proved that this was the Lords Supper. And how weak a ground this is for the obſervation of this day as a Sabbath, or more then any other day, or to limite the adminiſtration of the Supper to this day, I leave to the truly wiſe in heart to judge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But the Church had their gatherings upon the firſt day of the week, from which it appears that it was the day that they met together upon, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The words are theſe, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the firſt day of the week let every one lay by him in ſtore, as God hath proſpered him, that there be no gatherings when I come.</hi> Here is no proof for their meeting together, but rather on the contrary every one of them was to lay by him in ſtore as God had proſpered him; no publique gathering but private laying up; but becauſe the Apoſtle ſaith in the cloſe of the verſe, that there be no gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings when I come, therefore it is thought the Scripture can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſo underſtood, becauſe it would not prevent gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings: but is this fair when a Text of Scripture ſtands alone to put ſuch a ſenſe upon it, as doth plainly contradict the very letter of it, when it ſaith, let every one of you lay by him in ſtore? then to ſay the meaning is to have publique gatherings and but one ſtore, and would not the end of the Apoſtle be fully anſwered, namely, to have no gatherings if each of them did lay by them in a ſtore (as God had proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them in the world,) ready againſt the Apoſtle came, they knowing of his coming? and when he came was it not as ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to carry it with them to him, as for us to carry our Bibles to a meeting, and what need would there be then of gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings? And this way [of giving would not be Phariſee-like, but according to the words of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.11. <hi>Take heed
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151754:19"/>that you do not your alms before men to be ſeen of them, otherwiſe you have no reward of your Father which is in Heaven; but when thou doeſt thine almes let not thy left hand know what thy right hand doth,</hi> verſ. 3. <hi>that thine almes may be in ſecret, and thy Father which ſeeth in ſecret himſelf ſhall reward thee openly,</hi> ver. 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But <hi>John</hi> was in the ſpirit upon the Lords day, (and had that glorious revelation upon it) which is conceived to be the firſt day of the week, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1 10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true, <hi>John was in the ſpirit on the Lords day,</hi> but the queſtion will be what day that was; if any one of the ſeven it muſt be the Sabbath, for no other day is ſo called but it; God calls it his Holy Day, <hi>Iſay.</hi> 58.13. and Chriſt ſaith he is Lord even of the Sabbath day; and if ſo, then it is his day, for he is Lord of it, and that by way of eminency, not as ſome would have it to ſhew that he is Lord of every day, but as it is the Sabbath; for ſo it is ſaid the Son of Man is Lord even of the Sabbath day. So that this notion that the Lords day is the firſt day, is meerly taken up on truſt one from an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, without one word in the Scripture to prove it ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But it wil be yet objected by thoſe that are for no Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, from the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Let no man there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore judge you in meat or in drink, or in reſpect of a holy day, or of the new Moon, or of the Sabbath days, which are a ſhadow of things to come, but the body is of Chriſt;</hi> from whence it is concluded that the Sabbath was but a ſhadow,
<note place="margin">The Apoſtle ſpeaks here of ſuch Sabbaths as were a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of things to come, but the ſeventh day Sabbath was in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration of ſomething paſt to wit the work of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> and none are to be jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for not obſerving of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There were Holy-dayes and Sabbaths beſides the ſeventh day Sabbath, or the Sabbath of the Lord thy God, for ſo it is called in the commandment, as doth appear in <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit.</hi> 23.39. now becauſe it is implyed in the words of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle that Sabbaths were ſhadows and done away by the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt, doth it therefore follow that all Sabbaths were ſo, any more then where the words of the Apoſtle implies that men ſhall be ſaved, proves that all men ſhall be ſaved; and if we conſider the verſes before it will plainly appear that the Apoſtle is not ſpeaking of any of the Ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: in the 15. verſe the Apoſtle is ſpeaking to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, ſhewing how they were dead in their ſins, and in the uncircumciſion of their fleſh, but now quickened by Chriſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151754:19"/>and all their treſpaſſes forgiven them. In the 14. verſe he ſhews what further benefit they had by the death of Chriſt, bloting out the hand-writing of Ordinances, which was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, and contrary to us, he took it out of the way nail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to his croſs; and the Scripture upon which the obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is bottomed, hath its dependence upon this, and comes in with a therefore let no man judge you in meats and drinks, and ſo forth; as though the Apoſtle had ſaid, foraſmuch as Chriſt hath blotted out &amp; nailed to his croſs thoſe ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that were againſt you which are Gentiles, you are not to be judged for the non-performance of them. Now the Ten Commandments were never againſt the Gentiles nor contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to them, for the ſame Apoſtle ſaith the matter of them was written in their hearts, as was ſaid before, and they did by nature the things contained in them, and therefore they were not contrary to them; but circumciſion and other or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances ſtood as a wall againſt the Gentiles, which Chriſt brake down by taking them out of the way and nailing them to his croſs, having aboliſht in his fleſh the enmity even the Law of Commandments contained in Ordinances, for to make in himſelf of twain one new man ſo making peace that he might reconcile both unto God in one body by the Groſs, having ſlain the enmity thereby, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.15, 16. So that it is clear the Apoſtle is ſpeaking of ſuch Commandments as are contained in Ordinances, and not thoſe Commandments that are ſo eminently diſtinguiſht from Ordinances; but thoſe Ordinances which were againſt the Gentiles and made them and the Jews two, as meats and drinks, New-Moons and Holy-dayes, and Sabbath dayes, Chriſt by his blood having taken theſe away hath made them one; but that the Ten Commandments ſhould be ſtruck at there is no colour in this Scripture for it, or that the Sabbath ſhould only be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out from them, &amp; nailed to the Croſs with New-Moons, meats and drinks, and other ſhadows and Ordinances, which were againſt man, when as Chriſt ſaith the Sabbath was made for man; ſo that in this place there is no proof for the abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating of this Command of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But how is it that the Apoſtle ſaith <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.5, 6. that one man obſerves one day above another, another obſerves
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151754:20"/>every day alike, and yet he doth not blame either of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I make no doubt but if the controverſie here had been about the Sabbath, whether it were to be obſerved or no? but it would have been plainly expreſt and not paſt over ſo ſlightly: but the Apoſtle is ſpeaking of indifferent things, which men were not to be judged for their doing or not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and not of Commandments. But becauſe it is ſaid that ſome eſteem every day alike, therefore ſome conclude that this takes in the Sabbath day; but we muſt compare Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture with Scripture, and find out ſuch a ſenſe as may bring them into a harmony, and ſometimes interpret general terms by reſtrictive Scriptures: for inſtance, Chriſt bids his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples go preach the Goſpel to every Creature; we muſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it thus, to every creature that is in a capacity to hear the Goſpel: The Apoſtle ſaith that every Creature of God is good and nothing to be refuſed; now ſome are poiſon and are to be refuſed, but his meaning is every Creature that is eatable is good and not to be refuſed. So here every day is alike, that is every working day, which God hath made alike, but the ſeventh day he hath ſanctified and made it a Sabbath of reſt, and ſo not like the other; and this interpretation is according to the Scripture, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.4. <hi>Behold I will rain bread from Heaven for you, and the people ſhall go out and gather a certain rate every day:</hi> and in verſe 12. <hi>They gathered every morning every man according to his eating, yet on the Sabbath day there was none to gather.</hi> And in our common ſpeech it is ſo, we call the ſix dayes every day; men ſay, we work every day or we travil ſo far every day, when they mean only the ſix dayes that they count working dayes. So the Apoſtle ſpeaking to them that kept the Sabbath ſpeaks in the ſame language, and we have no ground to think otherwiſe, for there is no Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture that we find before this that hath any ſeeming diſlike againſt the obſervation of the Sabbath, but much on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> Ye obſerve dayes and years and times and months, I am afraid of you leaſt I have beſtowed upon you labour in vain, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.10, 11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This cannot be underſtood that the Apoſtle here ſtrikes at the meer obſervation of dayes, a thing of ſuch dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151754:20"/>conſequence, for he would not have them judged that obſerved one day above another, in <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.5, 6. and in this place he himſelf judges theſe as perſons that had ſo far degenerated that he was afraid that he had beſtowed upon them labour in vain, but it is manifeſt that theſe <hi>Galatians</hi> were gone back to circumciſion, &amp; ſo were debters to the whole Law ſeeking juſtification thereby, Chap. 5.2, 3, 4. and ſo they obſerved days and years according to the Law that was a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of good things to come, ſolemnizing the days &amp; months and years with thoſe things that were appointed for them, as burnt-offerings, meat-offerings, the waving of the ſheaf, the Paſſeover and unleavened bread, and the like, as you may ſee at large. <hi>Lev.</hi> 23.8, 9, 10, 11. and ſo on; for they could not be ſaid to obſerve times and months and yeers, according to the Law, except they did ſuch ſervice; and this gave the Apoſtle juſt ground to fear that he had beſtowed on them labour in vain: But to imagine that to obſerve the Sabbath according to the Commandment, or to obſerve a day voluntarily to the Lord, is ſo dangerous, is contrary both to Scripture &amp; reaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> We which believe are entred into reſt which the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath was but a Type of, as appears by the words of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If eternal reſt by faith be the Antitype of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, the Sabbath ceaſed to be in force to every man, ſo ſoon as they believed: which is ridiculous to think and contrary to the current of Scriptures; but the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>We which do believe do enter into reſt, for he that is entred into his reſt is ceaſed from his own works, as God did from his,</hi> verſ. 10. <hi>Let us labour therefore to enter into that reſt, leſt any man fall after the example of unbelief,</hi> verſ. 11. Mind this Chap. well and I am perſwaded you will ſee that the drift of the Apoſtle in men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning the ſeventh day here is but to amplifie, and ſet forth that perfect reſt which they that believe do and ſhall enjoy, of which the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> was but a Type, and to ſhew that Gods reſt was before the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> verſ. 4. and that yet there remains a reſt to the people of God: and as God did reſt the ſeventh day from all his works, ſo they that enter into reſt do ceaſe from their own works, as God did from his; and this is not as ſoon as men believe, for the Apoſtle provokes
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151754:21"/>himſelf and others to labour: to enter into it which were believers, and therefore if you will have the Sabbath a Type from this Scripture, though it is no where ſo called, it muſt be a Type of eternal reſt which Saints do enter into when they ceaſe from their own works, as God did from his, and that will not be till they lay down this Tabernacle, which will not hurt the thing aſſerted: And indeed I cannot deny but the Sabbath is an earneſt of that reſt, and Saints that are ſpiritual in the obſervation of it find it ſo, and of great uſe to put them in mind of that glorious reſt, as the bread and wine in the Supper of the Lord puts us in mind of the ſufferings of Chriſt; ſo this being a day of reſt and delight, being ſtript of all worldly incumbrances, and devoted to the Lord to pray unto him, and to praiſe his Holy Name, and to meditate up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Heaven and Heavenly glory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But many ſay if the Sabbath be in force, then the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty muſt needs be ſo, and then thoſe that do not keep it muſt be ſtoned; therefore this opinion is dangerous, and will lead Saints to deſtroy one another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is a very gaſtly objection, but indeed it is a very weak one; I do not find that any more then one was ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and it was for preſumptious breaking of the Sabbath: but ſuppoſe that penalty be in force, every Saint is not a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate to put it in execution; if a Saint ſhould kill a man, Saints as they are Saints are not to execute him, all that they can do is to endeavour his repentance, but it belongs to the true Magiſtrate to inflict the puniſhment: &amp; the penal Laws of God take hold of preſumptious ſinners, not for ſins of ignorance; and therefore it is not to be thought that any pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment will be inflicted upon any for breach of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath till it be univerſally acknowledged; ſo then if God hath annexed death to the breakers of it, doubtleſs it will be juſt, but we find in <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> time that although they had made a market-day of the Sabbath, <hi>Treading of Wine-preſſes, lading of Aſhes, and ſelling of all manner of proviſions upon it,</hi> yet he doth but contend with them, he contends with both Jews &amp; Gentiles, the Nobles of <hi>Judah</hi> and the men of <hi>Tyre,</hi> but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts no puniſhment upon either, <hi>Nehe.</hi> 13.15, 16, 17, 21. But what a ſtrange thing is this that men ſhould count it a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151754:21"/>opinion, to hold that the Sabbath is not in force be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the penalty; ſuppoſe it be ſo, the ſame may be ſaid of the reſt of the Commandments: for inſtance the firſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment is, <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other Gods but me;</hi> he that worſhipped a ſtrange God was to be put to death: now ſhall we not own this Commandment, becauſe the breakers of it were ſo puniſhed; again, he that ſheddeth mans blood, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed: now is there any danger in the own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this command, <hi>Thou ſhalt do no murder,</hi> becauſe the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment is in force too; again, <hi>the fifth Commandment is Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thy father and thy mother,</hi> but <hi>he that curſed father or me; ther was to be put to death:</hi> now ſhall we not honour father and mother, and ſo ſhall we break this Commandment, becauſe this puniſhment belongs to the breakers of it? So that this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection is of no weight nor uſe at all, except it be as a bears-skin put upon the truth to afright children away, leaſt they ſhould look into it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But we do not find any of the Apoſtles urge this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in any of their Epiſtles, namely,
<note place="margin">Or as it is in the margin of ſome Bibles, that Law which ſaid do not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Adultery, ſaid do not kill; ſo that the 10. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments are diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht from other Laws, and they are all of them to be kept, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſame Law-maker doth by one and the ſame Law com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand one as well as the other.</note> that the Sabbath day ſhould be obſerved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Neither do we find that the Apoſtles urged the 1.2. or 3. Command in particular as laid down in the Table, but they are frequently urged in the general, as in <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.12. Ch. 13.8, 9, 10. and generals comprehend particulars: and <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall keep the whole Law, and yet offend in one point is guilty of all;</hi> and he proves it thus, <hi>becauſe he that ſaith do not commit adultery, ſaith alſo do not kill: now if thou commit no adultery, yet if thou kill, thou art become a tranſgreſsor of the Law.</hi> The ſame argument may be drawn for the thing in hand, he that ſaith do not commit adultery, ſaith alſo keep the Sabbath; now if thou commit no adultery, yet if thou break the Sabbath, thou art become a tranſgreſſor of the Law, Chap. 2.10, 11. And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Circumciſion is nothing nor uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion is nothing, but the keeping of the Commandments of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.19. <hi>John</hi> ſaith in his firſt Epiſtle Chap. 5.2, 3. <hi>By this we know that we love the Children of God when we love God and keep his Commandments, for this is the love of God that we keep his Commandments, and his Commandments are not griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous;</hi> and if the Apoſtles had not ſpake a word to this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151754:22"/>in general nor in particular, 'tis no ground for us to lay it by, except the obſervation of it were forbidden, becauſe it is ſo plainly commanded by God, explained by Chriſt, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by his diſciples both before and after his death, as was ſaid before, and will further appear by and by.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> We do not find that any of the Churches kept the Sabbath.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That is no proof that they did not keep it, but 'tis clear that the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> kept it, though it is not plainly expreſt, for they were ſo zealous for the very cuſtoms, that <hi>Paul</hi> is counſelled to purifie himſelf, leaſt they ſhould be offended at him, <hi>Act.</hi> 21.21, 24. now if they were for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of thoſe things that were but ſhadows, there is no doubt but they were very ſtrict for the obſervation of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath; and if there were ſuch offence taken againſt <hi>Paul</hi> for preaching againſt circumciſion and the cuſtoms, we need not queſtion but if the Sabbath had been preached againſt, but we ſhould have heard a great noiſe of it in the Scriptures, and ſeen ſtrong convincing reaſons why it was aboliſht; and it is as clear that the Apoſtles kept the Sabbath ſince the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Chriſt as before. <hi>Paul went into the Synagogue on the Sabbath day and ſate down, and after the reading of the Law preacht the Goſpel,</hi> Act. 13.14, 15. <hi>and told them of the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of thoſe that dwelt at Jeruſalem; of the voice of the Prophets which were read every Sabbath day,</hi> verſ. 27. <hi>and the Gentiles beſought him that theſe words might be taught to them the next Sabbath,</hi> verſ. 42. <hi>And the next Sabbath came almoſt the whole City together to hear the word of God,</hi> verſ. 44. So that its clear that the Sabbath was <hi>Pauls</hi> reſting day and preaching day both to Jews and Gentiles, that being the day that the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles uſed to hear, and though they had a deſire to hear the ſame words again, yet it muſt be next Sabbath; and <hi>Paul</hi> ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fils their deſire and preaches to them the next Sabbath, and almoſt the whole City came to hear. Can we think that if there had been no Sabbath, that <hi>Paul</hi> would have counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced them ſo in their ignorance? Or if the firſt day had been a day that were obſerved, would he not have told them ſo? and that they might have heard the word before the next Sabbath: And when <hi>Paul</hi> came to <hi>Philippi</hi> a Gentile City,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151754:22"/>mind what is ſaid, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.12, 13. <hi>We were in that City abiding certain days, and on the Sabbath day we went out of the City by a river ſide where prayer was wont to be made, and we ſate down and ſpake unto the women that reſorted thither;</hi> The ſeventh day hath its title ſtill, as is ſaid by the ſpirit in the <hi>Acts,</hi> ſpeaking of certain dayes; this is ſingled out and called the Sabbath day with an account how they ſpent it, and the bleſſing they received upon it, they reſorted to the place of prayer and there they preached; and <hi>Lydias</hi> heart the Lord opened to attend to the words of <hi>Paul.</hi> And in <hi>Act.</hi> 17.2. it is ſaid, <hi>That Paul, as his manner was, went in unto them, and three Sabbath dayes reaſoned with them out of the Scriptures.</hi> And when <hi>Paul</hi> came to <hi>Corinth,</hi> which was a Gentile City, he found <hi>Aquila</hi> a Jew and his wife <hi>Priſcilla,</hi> and becauſe they were of the ſame craft he abode with them, and wrought, for by their oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupation they were Tent-makers, <hi>and he reaſoned in the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue every Sabbath day, and perſwaded the Jews and Greeks,</hi> Act. 18.2, 3, 4. So that its manifeſt that the <hi>Greeks</hi> kept the Sabbath as well as the Jews, and that though <hi>Paul</hi> wrought at his trade and made Tents, yet he reſted every Sabbath day; and as we have an account how he ſpent his time, namely in working at his trade, ſo we have an account how he ſpent this time to wit the Sabbath. Now if it be ſuch a ſtrong ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument for the obſervation of the firſt day, becauſe <hi>Paul</hi> preached upon it once; what is this for the obſervation of the ſeventh day, that <hi>Paul</hi> did not only preach conſtantly upon it? but where ever the Spirit ſpeaks of it he calls it the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day, without the leaſt hint that ſo he did to condeſcend to the weakneſs of others. And let it be ſhewed by the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture that the Apoſtles did countenance and own any ſhadow that was done away, ſo as they owned and countenanced the keeping of the Sabbath; and therefore we may follow the Apoſtles as they followed the Lord in this matter, though we have not a expreſs word that the Churches kept it. And indeed I think I may ſay in this caſe as the Apoſtles ſaid in another caſe, that it would have been ſuperflous for the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to have told any people in their time that ſuch or ſuch a Church kept the Sabbath; it being a truth not ſo much as queſtioned that we hear of, but Jew and Gentiles both ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151754:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>it. But now I ceaſe anſwering objections, having ſpoak to thoſe that are the moſt material of them that I have heard, and I ſhall proceed to another ground.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Conſider the bondage and ſlavery that both man and beaſt would be in if this doctrine were received for truth, would it no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> how ever have this tendency to bring the world more into Atheiſme? For men would not allow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, nor ſervants time to reſt in, nor to hear the word of God if they were perſwaded that there were no Sabbath; yea and the greateſt part of Saints are left to the mercy of mercyleſs men, moſt of them being children and wives and ſervants, and they cannot challenge a day in ſeven, nor a day in ſeventy, as their right to reſt upon and to worſhip the Lord in from any command of God if this doctrine be true that the Sabbath is aboliſht; and what is this but to bring a yoak of bondage upon us, that neither we nor our fathers were able to bear; we ſhould not ſo much as take notice of the time how it goes in probability, for the way of numbering is by ſevens. But ſome will ſay it is good to obſerve one day in ſeven, if it be not a conſtant day, that will be confeſſed for one to obſerve one day, and another to obſerve another day; others are for a ſeventh day to be conſtantly obſerved: but why not the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day which God hath commanded, for the ſeventh day is the Sabbath; it plainly appears that there is ſomething of the Table Law yet upon the Table of the hearts of moſt men though much worn out by much tranſgreſſion, for men gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally plead to have one day in ſeven to reſt in, and yet becauſe of cuſtome they contend againſt this Holy Juſt Law of God that was made in mercy for man. I am perſwaded in my ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry heart and that not without good ground, that if the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day had been obſerved as the firſt day is, that no man that owns the Scripture would have queſtioned whether it ought to be obſerved or no? or at leaſt no oppoſition would have been made againſt it; and when all is ſaid, cuſtom and worldly intereſt are the two great things that ſtand in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to it.</p>
            <p n="9">9. And laſtly, Conſider thoſe great and precious promiſes made to them that keep the Sabbath according to the inſide and ſpirituality of it; not that we are ſo to ſpiritualize it as
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151754:23"/>to make void the letter, but according to the letter as Chriſt doth: for inſtance <hi>Ye have heard,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>it hath been ſaid of old time, thou ſhalt not commit adultery; but I ſay unto you whoſoever looketh on a woman and luſteth after her hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted adultery with her in his heart,</hi> Mat. 5.28. Now if it be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery to luſt, doubtleſs it is to act, and this is forbidden in the Commandment, for the Commandment is, <hi>thou ſhall not commit adultery;</hi> but Chriſt unfolds this Commandment, and gives ſuch a ſenſe of it as the Scribes and Phariſees underſtood not. Again the ſixth Commandment is, <hi>Thou ſhalt do no mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> and <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>Whoſoever hateth his brother is a murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer,</hi> 1 Joh. 3.15. Now all murther was forbidden in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; but this was not underſtood to be murther, but <hi>John</hi> opens the ſpirituality of the command: and the ſame may be ſaid of the fourth command, <hi>Remember the Sabbath to keep it Holy;</hi> all ſervile work is forbidden in it, and that the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees underſtood; but they did not underſtand that works of mercy, as curing the ſick, healing the diſeaſed, might be done upon it: neither did they underſtand that inward and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual reſt that was held out in the command, as appears by the words of the Lord, <hi>Iſay.</hi> 58.13, 14. <hi>If thou turn away thy foot from the Sabbath, from doing thy pleaſure upon my Holy day, and call the Sabbath a delight, the Holy of the Lord honourable, and ſhalt honour him not doing thine own wayes, nor finding thine own pleaſure, nor ſpeaking thine own words.</hi> So that the Saints are not only to ceaſe from outward work in their callings, but alſo from works that are inward and ſpiritually wicked, that ſo the Sabbath might be a delight unto them, the Holy of the Lord honourable. And mark the promiſe that it is to ſuch Sabbath keepers, verſ. 14. <hi>Then ſhalt thou delight thy ſelf in the Lord, and I will cauſe thee to ride upon the high places of the earth, and will feed thee with the heritage of Jacob thy father, for the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it.</hi> Firſt, they ſhall delight themſelves in the Lord, and that will make the Sabbath a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light. Secondly, they ſhall ride upon the high places of the earth; the high places of the earth holds forth (as I conceive) the great oppoſition whether of great and mighty men, or great walled Cities, according to that in <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.28. it hath an alluſion to Iſraels ſubduing the land of <hi>Canaan, Deut</hi> 32.13.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151754:24"/>thou ſhalt ride upon them that is ſubdue and conquer them, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.12. <hi>They ſhall tread upon their high places:</hi> as in <hi>Deu.</hi> 33.39. <hi>They ſhall be as aſhes under the ſoles of their feet,</hi> Mal. 4.3. Now when did the Lords people do ſuch work as this ſince this propheſie? or is it not yet to be fulfilled?</p>
            <p>Again conſider what the Lord ſaith, <hi>Iſay</hi> 56.6, 7. <hi>Alſo the ſons of the ſtranger that joyn themſelves to the Lord to ſerve him, and to love the name of the Lord to be his ſervants, every one that keepeth the Sabbath from pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it, and taketh hold of my Covenant, even them will I bring to my Holy mountain, and make them joyful in my houſe of prayer; their burnt-offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings and their ſacrifices ſhall be accepted upon mine Altar, for mine houſe ſhall be called an houſe of prayer for all people.</hi> By the ſons of the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers I underſtand is here meant Gentiles, who were ſtrangers to the Common-wealth of Iſrael and a far off, but now made nigh by the blood of Chriſt, and ſo they joyn themſelves to the Lord and ſerve him, and love the name of the Lord; theſe are ſuch as keep the Sabbath, and take hold of Gods Covenant, and it is ſuch a Sabbath as may be poluted, and therefore not Chriſt as ſome would have it; now the promiſes that are made to theſe ſtrangers, do look at clear Goſpel times.</p>
            <p>They ſhall be brought into Gods Holy Mountain and there be made joyful, when its ſo mountainous that its the houſe of prayer for all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or for all nations, as Chriſt ſaith <hi>Mar.</hi> 11.17. <hi>Iſay</hi> 56.8. again in verſ 2. <hi>Bleſſed be the man that doth this, and the ſon of man that layeth hold on it that keepeth the Sabbath from poluting it, and keepeth his hand from doing any evil; thus ſaith the Lord unto the Eunuches that keep my Sabbath, and chuſe the things that pleaſe me, and take hold on my Covenant, even unto them will I give in my houſe a name and a place better then of ſons and daughters; I will give them an everlasting name that ſhall not be cut off,</hi> verſ. 2, 4, 5. The Eunuches are ſuch as care for things that pleaſe the Lord, when the married cares for the things that pleaſe his wife, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.32, 33. or according to that in <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.4. <hi>Theſe are they that were not defilled with women, for they are Virgins, theſe are they that follow the Lamb whereſoever he goeth; they ſing as it were a new ſong, and yet it is old, its the ſong of Moſes the ſervant of God, and the ſong of the Lamb.</hi> Rev. 15.2, 3. And when two parts ſhall be cut off and dye, <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.8. the Eunuches that keep the Sabbath ſhall have an everlaſting name, which ſhall not be cut off.</p>
            <p>Now let us not think it incredible that the Sabbath ſhould be yet in force, becauſe it hath been ſo long laid by; it hath been ſo with other truths and ſo with this before now, it ſeemed to be ſo out of knowledge with Iſrael in the wilderneſs, that when the people had gathered twice as much Manna on the ſixth day, they did not underſtand the meaning of it, but the Nobles came and told <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 16.22. and <hi>Moſes</hi> told them the thing that the Lord had ſaid, that to morrow was the reſt of the Holy Sabbath: And alſo after their coming out of <hi>Babylon</hi> when they had built the houſe of God and ſet it in order, placing the Prieſts and Levits, and had choſen faithful men to diſtribute the maintainance to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151754:24"/>their brethren, <hi>Neh.</hi> 13.10, 13. In a word their reformation was much about the light of ours, and is confeſſed by the enlightened that it was a Type of this reformation that the Lord hath begun amongſt us in theſe Iſles, namely in bringing his people our of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and building up of <hi>Sion;</hi> and indeed as their ſins and ours are alike in many things ſo in this, namely, in breaking the fourth Commandment; for <hi>Nehemiah</hi> ſaith in Chap. 13.15. <hi>That in thoſe dayes he ſaw in Judah ſome treading Wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes on the Sabbath, and lading of Aſſes, and bringing of Sheafs, as alſo Wine-grapes and Figs, and all manner of burthens which they brought into Jeruſalem upon the Sabbath day, and he teſtified againſt them in the day wherein they ſold victuals:</hi> notwithſtanding all the reformation yet this was ſeen in <hi>Judah,</hi> they had layed by the obſervation of the Sabbath, and had made it a common working Market-day, as you may ſee at large in that Chap. It was not in vain therefore that the Lord ſaid, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Sabbath,</hi> he foreſeeing how it would be ſleighted and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, not only by thoſe that were brought out of litteral <hi>Babylon,</hi> but alſo by thoſe that ſhould be brought out of ſpiritual <hi>Babylon</hi> in the latter dayes: but when the day of the Lord burns as an oven, it will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred to ſome purpoſe, <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.4. In the mean time the Lord is ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up ſome of his poor babes and ſucklings, ſuch he is pleaſed uſually to diſcover truth unto at the firſt breaking; out of it, and they are to contend for it though in much weakneſs.</p>
            <p>But a word to the beginning and ending of the Sabbath, there are va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious apprehenſions about it, which for brevity ſake I ſhall omit; the Scripture is plain, that from evening, to evening, is the ſet time; or from the going down of the Sun, to the going down of the Sun: this is clear from the beginning, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.5. <hi>The evening and the morning was the first day:</hi> evening and morning make a compleat natural day, and the even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing goeth before the morning, becauſe the darkneſs was before the light, verſ. 1, 2, 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But ſome will ſay it is not ſaid the evening and the morning was the ſeventh day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If the evening and the morning be the ſixth day, the evening and the morning muſt needs be the ſeventh day, unleſs we ſhould think that the ſeventh day hath no night belonging to it; ſome think that the reaſon why no mention is made of the evening of the ſeventh day, is, becauſe the Sabbath is a day of joy and delight, or an earneſt of the new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate wherein ſhall be no night, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.25. Night doth fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in the Scripture hold forth a ſtare of affliction, but the Sabbath is a holy ſanctified time, on it the Creatour reſted and was refreſhed, and commanded the obſervation of it that his creatures might be refreſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nehemiah</hi>'s practiſe is ſufficient proofe for the beginning of the Sabbath at evening, Chap. 13.19. who when the gates of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> began to be dark, he commanded them to be ſhut till after the Sabbath. And if you would know when the evening begins the Evangeliſt doth inform you, <hi>Mark.</hi> 1.32. <hi>At even when the Sun did ſet they brought unto him all that were diſeaſed;</hi> when the Sun doth ſet then begins the evening, then
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151754:25"/>begins the holy reſt or ſeventh day Sabbath; and ſo the diſciples of Chriſt began the Sabbath, and ſo the Lords ancient people celebrate the Sabbath unto this day.</p>
            <p>But what confuſion are they in who ſay the Sabbath was changed from the ſeventh day to the firſt day, and yet obſerve neither but pare of the firſt day and part of the ſecond day, for they begin their Sabbath at midnight when a good part of the firſt day is ſpent, and they end at midnight when a good part of the ſecond day is ſpent, and yet they will have this to be a Sabbath, yea and a firſt day Sabbath, and will highly charge a man to be an offender if he work one hour upon the firſt day, though themſelves work five; and thus we ſee how Antichriſt hath changed times as well as Laws, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.28. a firſt day Sabbath in ſtead of the ſeventh day Sabbath, in ſtead of from even to evening, from midnight to midnight, when moſt are faſt a ſleep, being inſenſible of the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their Sabbath, or of the ending of it.</p>
            <p>But bleſſed be the Lord that he hath revealed this his ancient, uſeful, honorable truth, to wit, the Holy ſeventh day Sabbath, notwithſtanding all the inventions of Antichriſt to bury it in oblivion, and that he is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſeparate a remnant, that are reſolved to ſearch and try their ways, and to turn unto him, to follow him in the wayes of his precepts, (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the dragons wrath,) who will not take things upon truſt, nor go upon the legs of men, but will try all things, and hold faſt that which is good, for they are virgins, and the Lamb they will follow though their company be ſmall and their charges great: they will not be afraid of the Sabbath becauſe it was given to the Jews, no more then they are afraid of the <hi>Adoption, and the glory, and the promiſes,</hi> and the other nine lively Oracles, which were all given to the Jews, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.4. And this I may modeſtly ſay to the praiſe of the Lord of the Sabbath, and without boaſting, that if the Saints did know how the Lord delights to meet with his people in this way of obedience in celebrating the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, they would ſoon <hi>call the Sabbath a delight, the Holy of the Lord ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable,</hi> and honour him by ceaſing from their own works, as God did from his, and do thoſe works which are ſuteable for the bleſſed ſeaſon. But I ſhall ſay no more at preſent ſave only this, that who ever they are that would follow the Lord in this appointment of his, they muſt labour much in the ſtrength of his ſpirit to get this world under them, for it ſtands in direct oppoſition to earthly men, and earthly principles; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore pray with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.36. <hi>Incline mine heart unto thy te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies, and not to covetouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
